Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project
2019-2024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York University. Asian/Pacific/American Studies Program and Institute
TAM.837
.1 Linear Feet in 3 folders in shared manuscript box
106 Gigabytes in 450 computer files
The A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project is a documentation project focused on the COVID-19 pandemic, specifically the ways the pandemic impacted Asian/Pacific/American (A/P/A) communities in New York City and nationally. The core principles guiding the project include intersectionality and cross-racial solidarity with other communities of color who suffer the effects of structural racism and state violence. The Records of the A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project (dated 2019-2024) consists of materials created and collected by the A/P/A Institute at New York University, in collaboration with Tomie Arai, Lena Sze, Vivian Truong, and Diane Wong. Materials include oral history interviews, zines, poetry, fliers, brochures, photographs, and short videos. The collection also includes a copy of Bittersweet: A Pandemic Sketchbook, a comic by Nuyên Khôi Nguyễn, and ephemera documenting the activities of Khmer Girls in Action (KGA).
Historical Note
The A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project is a documentation project focused on the COVID-19 pandemic, specifically the ways the pandemic impacted Asian/Pacific/American (A/P/A) communities in New York City and nationally. The project was developed by the Asian/Pacific/American Institute at New York University, in collaboration with Tomie Arai, Lena Sze, Vivian Truong, and Diane Wong. The project's goal was to account for a gap in documentation about the experiences of A/P/A communities in relation to the COVID-19 pandemic, as well as a historical pattern where the experiences of A/P/A individuals and communities were often un- or under-documented. The core principles guiding the project include intersectionality and cross-racial solidarity with other communities of color who suffer the effects of structural racism and state violence. The killings of George Floyd, Tony McDade, Ahmaud Arbery, Breonna Taylor, and many other Black people by police, and subsequent protests in response to these events, were significant and an explicit context of the project.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into a single file listing in alphabetical order by name or organization.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project (dated 2019-2024) consists of materials created and collected by the A/P/A Institute at New York University, in collaboration with Tomie Arai, Lena Sze, Vivian Truong, and Diane Wong. The interviews and supplementary materials found in the collection document the experiences of Asian/Pacific/American (A/P/A) community members as subjects of their own stories and offer opportunities for parallels and possibilities for solidarity across communities. Other subject areas include the increased anti-Asian violence and xenophobia of the pandemic, and the ways COVID-19 disproportionately impacted Pacific Islander communities, as well as Asian immigrant services and healthcare workers. The presence of materials connecting growing anti-Asian fears during the COVID-19 pandemic to the Black Lives Matter movement also highlights the ways racial discrimination united these communities.
Materials in the collection include oral history interviews and transcripts; artistic works, zines, and poetry; fliers and brochures; and photographs and short videos. Not all oral histories are accompanied by digital ephemera and not all ephemera relates to a particular interview.
The collection also contains physical materials including a copy of Bittersweet: A Pandemic Sketchbook (a comic) by Nuyên Khôi Nguyễn, and ephemera documenting the activities of Khmer Girls in Action (KGA).
When available, biographical information about project participants has been included in the inventory. A brief description of what each participant contributed to the project has also been noted in the inventory, when information is available.
Conditions Governing Access
Access varies across the collection for the oral history interviews and the conditions governing access to those materials are documented at the level of the individual narrators. Other non-oral history interview materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Asian/Pacific/American Institute in May 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.035. Physical materials were donated by Khmer Girls in Action and Nuyên Khôi Nguyễn to A/P/A Voices coordinators and transferred to Tamiment in August 2024; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2025.008 and 2025.009, respectively.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Oral histories (literary works); COVID-19 (Disease); Solidarity; Racism -- United States.; Asian Americans.; Discrimination against Asian Americans.; Asian Americans -- Political activity; Asian Americans -- Race identity; Asian Americans -- Social conditions.; Zines; Video recordings.; Art.; New York University. Asian/Pacific/American Studies Program and Institute
- #IAMNOTAVIRUS, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_1
  Historical Note
  The #IAMNOTAVIRUS Campaign was part of an artist led grassroots initiative founded by Mike Keo. The initiative's goal is to perform impactful work on inter-ethnic solidarity and an interracial coalition by connecting Black, Indigenous, and People of Color (BIPOC) communities through storytelling. The #IAMNOTAVIRUS Campaign reclaimed the Asian American story, displayed it through an equity lens, and brought together a community of intersectional solidarity.
  Scope and Contents
  Materials include #IAMNOTAVIRUS posters, a public service announcement video by Mike Keo, and a copy of A Mental Wellness Activity Book for Asian Americans sponsored by #IAMNOTAVIRUS and the University of Connecticut's Asian and Asian American Studies Institute (AAASI).
- Ali, Shirin, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_2
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Lena Sze on August 6, 2020. In her interview, Shirin Ali, an Indian American Muslim partnered woman, psychiatrist, and psychoanalyst in New York City spoke about her experiences as shaped by those identifications. Other topics in the interview include her experiences of treating patients' mental health during the pandemic, particularly during the intense wave of COVID-19 in New York City in March and April 2020, and during the George Floyd protests. Ali also discusses her experiences volunteering remotely at a hospital in the Bronx and discusses her observations of the disparate level of resources at different institutions. Finally, Ali discusses her feelings of staying in New York City during COVID-19; being in the health field; and the possible long-term effects of this pandemic, i.e. grief and trauma, on health care professionals and society at large.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The transcript, audio files, and video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room or remotely.
  Biographical Note
  Shirin Ali is an Indian American Muslim woman, a psychiatrist, and psychoanalyst in New York City.
- Arai, Tomie, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_3
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Lena Sze on April 8, 2021. A "Stay Strong" poster, which was created for W.O.W. Project's "Love Letters to Chinatown" project is also included.
  In her interview, Tomie Arai reflects on her experiences during this pandemic. She offers her views of the protests following the murder of George Floyd; the tactical differences between 1970s activists and current activists, especially abolitionists, whom she is inspired by; anti-Blackness within Asian American communities; Black-Asian solidarity and incidents of anti-Asian violence; and some of the internal politics of Manhattan's Chinatown. She also reflects on aging; her and her friends' vulnerability as older people to COVID-19; and COVID-19's health and emotional impact on her as it has caused her to think about her own mortality and body of work.
  Tomie Arai is a New Yorker and Japanese American artist living on the Upper West Side of New York City. She is a long-time artist involved in social movements and community-based organizing. She has been involved in some pivotal Asian American cultural collectives such as Basement Workshop. Arai also collaborates with local communities to create visual narratives that give meaning to the spaces we live in. Along with Betty Yu and Mansee Kang, Arai is a co-founder of the Chinatown Art Brigade and was a 2020 Transnational Fellow with Monument Lab, an initiative that reimagines public space through stories of social justice and equity.
- Asian American Bar Association of New York (AABANY), circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_4
  The Asian American Bar Association of New York was formed in 1989 as a not-for-profit corporation to represent the interests of New York Asian-American attorneys, judges, law professors, legal professionals, legal assistants, paralegals, and law students. The mission of AABANY is to improve the study and practice of law, and the fair administration of justice for all by ensuring the meaningful participation of Asian-Americans in the legal profession.
  Materials include legal relief flyers in English, Korean, and Chinese; and reports on anti-Asian hate during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Asian American Feminist Collective, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_5
  Materials include copies of the zine, "Feminist Antibodies: Care in the Time of Coronavirus." The zine was an attempt to find meaning during the coronavirus crisis through long-standing practices of care that came out of Asian American histories and politics. To create the zine, the Asian American Feminist Collective gathered first-hand accounts and analyses from their communities including: health, service workers, and caregivers on the frontlines; students, journalists, and organizers; and people living with chronic illness. Together, this collection of stories, essays, and artwork attempted to illustrate how this community experienced, resisted, and grappled with a viral outbreak that had been racialized as Asian.
- Asian American Writers' Workshop (AAWW), circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_6
  Materials include a video entitled "Lit Lunch," which was an interview series featuring writers, journalists, and organizers who talked about their work. This event occurred on May 27, 2020 and featured Huiying B. Chan and Emily Mock.
- Asian Pacific Environmental Network (APEN), circa 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_7
  APEN's mission is to bring together a collective voice to develop an alternative agenda for environmental, social, and economic justice. Although APEN holds this vision of environmental justice for all people, APEN's primary focus is on Asian immigrant and refugee communities.
  Materials include videos of vigils held in Atlanta, Georgia in the wake of the 2021 spa shootings.
- Attia, Mohamed, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_8
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Loubna Qutami on September 16, 2020. The interview details Mohamed Attia's experience as an immigrant street vendor and the myriad of systemic injustices the community has experienced even prior to the COVID-19 pandemic. Attia explains how those challenges were exacerbated following the outbreak of the pandemic and speaks to the different types of services and programs his organization has been offering the Street Vendor Community.
  Mohamed Attia is an organizer with the Street Vendors Project in New York City. Attia came to the U.S. from Egypt in 2009, began working in local bodegas, and then as a street vendor. Through firsthand experience, Attia witnessed the hardships he and other street vendors from diverse immigrant backgrounds experienced including the difficulty in accessing food vendor permits as a result of discriminatory policies at federal, state, and local levels. Frustrated with the exclusions and oppressions the street vendor community experienced, Attia was eager to contribute to change and joined the Street Vendors Project as a general member in order to advocate for street vendors rights. After several years as a general member, Attia joined the Street Vendors Project as a staff member. Since then, he has been a part of a number of campaigns that seek to secure the rights of street vendors as an important economic, social, and cultural sector of New York City.
- Begum, Zenat, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_9
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Zaim Alam on January 22, 2021. During the interview, Zenat Begum spoke extensively about how since the beginning of the pandemic, rather than shelter in place doing nothing, she instead pivoted to the question what Playground Coffee Shop could do to help the community. Distributing personal protective equipment (PPE) became a significant part of Playground's mutual aid efforts, particularly during the protests of summer 2020. Begum was also involved with establishing a community fridge, which was setup in spring 2020, and has since been replicated across the borough.
  Zenat also discusses moments of exhaustion and sheer misfortune she's experienced during the pandemic, and her ability to remain positive. She expresses her belief that while it will be impossible for things to go back to normal post-pandemic, and as long as we sustainably put into action all we have been angered by and fought for, there is light at the end of the tunnel.
  Zenat Begum is an entrepreneur, activist, and native New Yorker of Bangladeshi origin. In 2016, she opened Playground Coffee Shop in Brooklyn's Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood. Begum and her team have further leaned in to serve the community by hosting chess classes, financial literacy workshops, community dinners, and more. During the COVID-19 pandemic, Begum and her peers established an initiative to set up refrigerators with free produce throughout Brooklyn, further demonstrating her mission to serve her community.
- Bernabe, Thria, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_10
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Rosario Joaquin on July 6, 2020. During the interview, Thria Bernabe describes the impact the pandemic had on her as an individual and the impact it had on her community in Queens. She describes a few of her mutual aid projects, including providing childcare for her emergency room colleagues; and donating profits from her art sales to a rotating list of COVID-19 relief funds and Black-led organizations, such as the Loveland Foundation Therapy Fund. She explains the challenges of living with an immunodeficiency during a pandemic, including facing medication shortages as various drugs were rumored to cure or prevent COVID-19; and making the ultimate decision to leave Queens and return to her family's home in New Jersey, where she could better protect herself from the virus. Bernabe ends her interview describing how art, her friends, family, and community brought her hope; and how she leads with the following guiding principle: we all deserve love, care, and happiness.
  Thria Bernabe is an artist and organizer from New Jersey. She is a graduate of New York University's Rory Meyers School of Nursing and works as a medical scribe for NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital. When the COVID-19 outbreak began in the United States, Bernabe was living in Queens and working in an emergency room.
- Cabiles, Moana, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_11
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on December 2, 2020. In her interview, Moana Cabiles shares her experiences as a Native Hawaiian community leader in La Mesa in San Diego, CA. When shelter-in-place was announced in California, Moana and her extended family were preparing for a carefully-planned family vacation in Europe, but due to COVID-19, the family had to cancel these plans and this overlapped with the beginning of other significant shifts that emerged due to the pandemic.
  Cabiles discusses changes in her work due to COVID-19 and the shelter-in-place order; and how the virtual shift to online communication, i.e. using Zoom, changed the social dynamic and relationship-building components of her work. In particular, she emphasizes the difficulty of contacting elected officials. She also discusses challenges faced by her children as they navigated online learning and school; and the challenges faced by Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander (NHPI) elders who do not use the Internet, email, or phones to remain in contact with others. Cabiles also discusses challenges related to Black Lives Matter (BLM) and the particular ways her community was impacted by protests. Though she supported BLM, she shares her anxieties and concerns regarding the violence incited by protests. Cabiles closes the interview by emphasizing the necessity of mental health support and social support resources.
  The transcript and video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room or remotely.
  Moana Cabiles is a Native Hawaiian community leader in La Mesa in San Diego, CA. Cabiles is a public health advocate and a member of the Community Services Commission in La Mesa. She specifically works with households impacted by smoking.
- Chang, Han-hua, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_12
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Sarah Nguyen on March 24, 2021. Two poems titled "Walking Home" and "Photographic Justice" are also included. During his interview, Han-hua Chang discusses the initial onset of COVID-19 during the school year and how he took the pandemic seriously from very early on. Chang talks at length about his school's lackluster response to the pandemic, insensitivity of trauma training in relation to Asian students, dismissals of his own concerns, and lack of discussion around the political turmoil the country had been experiencing. Chang expresses how he misses in-person teaching, and complains his school provided few resources for faculty and students to better facilitate online learning.
  Chang frames many of his experiences during the pandemic through those of his parents. His father died five years ago after experiencing hospice and hospital care; and his mother was in and out of hospitals during the pandemic. Chang's mother contracted COVID-19 in a nursing home and was mistreated by health care professionals throughout her time in various care facilities. Impacted by her past experience as a nurse for the Allies in China during World War II, Chang's mother was very cautious during the pandemic before her health declined.
  Chang discusses his challenging experience getting the vaccine and different parts of his daily routine during the pandemic. Chang, who lives in Columbia University's Law School Dorms, was disturbed by the lack of safety and sensitivity displayed by the college students, who continued to throw parties and not wear masks in the hallways, despite the presence of vulnerable individuals. Chang concludes the interview talking about his experiences in organizing and how he believes the current state of politics has radicalized and united the left.
  Han-hua Chang is a math teacher at John J. Pershing IS 220 in Sunset Park, NY and lives in the Upper West Side of Manhattan, on the Columbia University campus. He used to be a vice president and organizer for the 1199 SEIU union.
- Chang, Kyle, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_13
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Mi Hyun Yoon on March 26, 2021. In his interview, Kyle Chang discusses growing up in Southeast Michigan in Macomb Township. Chang contrasts the hostility of his conservative hometown with how open minded his parents were, and recounts how he came to be adopted by his working-class midwestern Catholic parents. Chang recounts how the pandemic affected his family as he has had to navigate caring for his mother after his father's death in 2006 – something that was complicated by the pandemic due to the distance of Texas and Michigan.
  Kyle Chang is a Korean American adoptee who lives in Frisco, TX and works as a user experience designer.
- Chau, Monyee, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_14
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on August 21, 2020. Examples of Monyee Chau's artwork is also included.
  In this interview, Chau explains how COVID-19 impacted Chinatown residents, how her personal response to anti-Asian racism raised her political consciousness, and became the reason for her current cultural activism. Chau talks at length about her work against gentrification and the ways in which crime, violence, and gentrification are critical issues that were brought into clear focus during COVID-19. Chau also discusses her artwork including a poster she donated to the A/P/A Voices Project that displays the message 'We're all built on resilience. We will Survive this too," which has been shared and posted in Chinatowns internationally. Chau also talks about her influences as an artist and describes the process behind a zine they created for the Wing Luke Museum about COVID-19. The zine features portraits of Chau's father and asks the question: "Will we be able to bounce back from this?" The zine was been used as a fundraiser for Wing Luke and has raised several thousand dollars for the Museum.
  Monyee Chau is a Seattle-based contemporary Taiwanese and Chinese American artist. Chau is a resident of Seattle's International District and grew up in Seattle's Chinatown. Chau explores the journey of healing through decolonization and reconnecting with her roots and ancestors through a variety of mediums. She has shown and curated multiple shows at Cornish College of the Arts, Pilchuck Glass School, Wing Luke Museum, Bellevue Arts Museum, and various exhibitions throughout Seattle. Chau has been the recipient of multiple Pilchuck scholarships, Cornish's Art Merit scholarship, nominations to the Outstanding Student Achievement in Contemporary Sculpture, and the Corning award.
  As of 2020, Chau was a member of several organizations calling for community policing and volunteers with a Community Night Watch to patrol the streets. These patrols were founded in honor on Don Chin, a community hero who lost his life protecting Chinatown.
- Chau, Sabrina Mon-Yee, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_15
  Materials include a poster titled "Resilience," which was a response to white nationalists stickers that had been appearing in Seattle's Chinatown International District as a fear tactic designed to intimidate the community; a comic titled "A Comic on Resiliency," which was made as part of a fundraiser for the Wing Luke Museum; a takeout menu style zine on the history of Chinese immigrants in America creating Chinatowns across the nation titled "Chinatowns In America - And The Racism That Built Them;" and a PowerPoint with other art made by Chau.
- Chiu, Yucan, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_16